<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation concernynge the Kynges style made the. XXIII. day of Ianuary, the XXXIII. yere of his maiesties most gracious reygne.</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1542-01-23</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1542</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69298</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7797</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108884</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844536</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844536</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9359</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69298)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9359)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 10:13, 152:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation concernynge the Kynges style made the. XXIII. day of Ianuary, the XXXIII. yere of his maiesties most gracious reygne.</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1542-01-23</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1509-1547 : Henry VIII)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Thomas Berthelet regius impressor excudebat. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1542]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Adds King of Ireland to Henry VIII's style.</note>
                  <note>Regarding Berthelet's delivery of copies of this and some later proclamations, see Arber II.51 ff.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Society of Antiquaries.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reels 10 and 152 (Society of Antiquaries copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry --  VIII, --  King of England, 1491-1547 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  16th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="royal_proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:9359:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A PROCLAMATION concernyng the Kynges ſtyle, made <date>the. XXIII. day of Ianuary, the XXXIII. yere of his maieſties moſte gracious reygne.</date>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE VVE BE IVSTELY</hi> and rightfully kinge of out Realme of Irelande, and ought to haue the title ſtile and name therof by righte of inheritaunce, and the non vſe therof in our ſtyle hath cauſed moche diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, rebellion, dyſcention, and ſedition in our ſayd realme, to the great impouery ſhyng and peryl of diſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the ſame, if we had not for the redreſſe therof, put to our kyngly hand, as we haue done, in ſuch wyſe, as by reaſon therof our ſayde realme (thankes be to god) is no we broughte and reduced to better order peace and ciuilitie, than it hath ben many yeres paſt. <hi>AND</hi> for as moche as our louynge ſubiectes of our ſayd realme, both the prelates nobles and commons, do thynke and determyne, that the good eſtate, peace, and tranquyllitie, wherein our ſayde realme nowe ſtandeth. ſhall the better and longer contynewe, yf we wolde as we ought of ryghte, accepte and take vppon vs the title and name of kynge of the ſame: whiche to do all our ſayde ſubiectes, of our ſayde realme, by their mutual aſſentes, by auctoritie of parlya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment holden within the ſame, haue agreed and aſſented vnto, and moſte inſtantly deſyred vs, that the ſayde title and name of kynge of Irelande, togyther with our ſayde hole realme, ſhuld be vnyted and annexed to our imperiall crowne of our realme of Englande. To whiche their deſyres and humble requeſtes, for the better conſecuation of the good peace of our ſayde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme, we haue aſſented, and haue cauſed for that purpoſe our ſtile to be altered and reformed, aſwell in the latine as in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſhe tungue, as hereafter foloweth. <hi>HENRICVS octauus dei gratia Angliç Franciae &amp; Hibernie rex, fidei defenſor, &amp; in terra eccleſiae Anglicanae &amp; Hibernicae ſupremum caput. HENRY</hi> the, <hi>VIII,</hi> by the grace of god kynge of Englande, Fraunce, and Irelande, defendour of the ſaythe, and of the churche of England and alſo of Ireland in erthe the ſupreme heed.</p>
            <p>And to the intent that our ſayd ſubiectes ſhuld not be ignoraunt of the alteration of our ſayd, in forme as is aforeſayde, we haue cauſed this preſent proclamation to be made, and by the ſame wyll and commaunde all and ſynguler our officers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices and miniſters, and all other our ſubiectes and reſiauntes within this our realme of Englande, and elles where, within any our domynyons, that they ſhall accepte, take, and vſe oure ſtyle, in forme aboue wrytten, in lyke forme, as they vſed and accepted oure olde ſtyle before this alteration. Neuer the leſſe, to the intente that noo dyſcorde varyaunce occaſyon. trouble, ympechemente, or moleſtation ſhoulde be had or made to any our Iuſtyces, offycers, minyſters, and other oure ſubiectes or reſyauntes, before they maye haue conuenyent knowledge of the chaunge and alteration of our late ſtile: we are therfore pleaſed &amp; contented, that none of our ſayde Iuſtices officers miniſters ſubiectes or other reſiantes within our realme of England, the dominion of wales, Calais; and of theyles of Ierſay &amp; Carnyſay, for omyttyng of our ſayd title and name of kyng of Ireland in wryttes patentes proces or other writinges, to be paſſed vnder any our ſeales, or for non acceptation or miſ acceptation therof, or for any offence touching the ſame, done or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, or to be done or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, before the laſt day of Apryl nexte comynge, ſhall be vexed troubled impeched, or by any wyſe moleſted or troubled, but that all wryttes patentes proces or other wrytynges that be paſſed or ſhall paſſe vnder any our ſeales, before the ſayde laſte daye of Apryll, wherin ſhall happen our ſayde title and name of kyng of Irelande to be omytted, ſhall be taken conſtrued accepted and admytted to be of the ſame force, ſtrength, qualitie, and condition in all thynges, as they were before the ſayde title and name of kynge of Irelande was annexed to our ſtile. And that the non acceptation or myſacceptation of our ſayde title and name of kynge of Ireland, or any actes or thynges done, or that ſhall chaunce to be done before the ſayd laſte day of Apryll, by any our ſubiectes or reſiaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, towthynge or concernyng our ſayd title or name of kynge of Irelande, ſhall be conſtrued and expounded any offence or occaſion of trouble to any of our ſayde ſubiectes or reſiauntes: any thynge conteyned in this proclamation, or any thyng that ſhall be expreſſed in the ſame, or any other thynge or thynges to the contrary therof in any wiſe not withſtandynge.</p>
            <closer>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> GOD SAVE THE KYNGE.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="license">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Thomas Berthelet regius impreſſor excudebat. Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
